@就是我的u@
Yes, this is home.
@就是地球
This is Earth.
找不到熟悉的大
Having trouble finding a familiar continent?
@是因檫^去的地球cF在完全不同
The past is another planet. Actually, many.
而在我_下的 就是宇宙大爆炸以淼乃有rg
I'm standing on the great expanse of time that has elapsed since the Big Bang.
榱烁好地理解大爆炸後l生了什N
In order to think about it,
我把rg嚎s成1年
we've compressed it all into a single year.
F在是宇宙年v上的12月23的清晨
It's the early morning of December 23 on this Cosmic Calendar of ours,
大s3|5千f年前
or about 350 million years ago,
r我的世界才40|q
when our world was a mere four billion years old.
地球看上去完全不同
Earth looks so different.
你完全J不出
You might not even know the place.
天上的星星也筒涣四
The stars wouldn't help you.
r的星座也和F在的不一
Even the constellations would have been different back then.
恐要在1|多年後才出F
The dinosaurs were still more than 100 million years in the future.
那r候也]有B ]有花
There were no birds, no flowers.
就B空舛疾灰
And the air was different, too.
大又械难舛瓤涨敖^後地高
The atmosphere had more oxygen than at any other time in Earth's history,  before or since.
@使得昆x可以L得比F在大得多
This allowed insects to grow much larger than they do today.
怎N@
How?
昆x]有肺
Insects don't have lungs.
它由身w上ν獾拈_口@得生命必的氧
Life-giving oxygen is taken in through openings in the outside of their bodies
然後通^管道Wj鞅槿身
and transported through a network of tubes.
如果昆xL得太大
If an insect were too large,
@些管道的外就吸收M所有的氧
the outer reaches of these tubes would absorb all the oxygen
氧饩o法到_炔康钠鞴
before it could ever get to its internal organs.
但是在石炭o
But during the Carboniferous Period,
距今2.9-3.55|年
大拥难舛仁乾F在的杀
the atmosphere had almost twice the oxygen as today.
昆x可以L得很大
Insects could then grow much bigger
依然可以@得足虻难
and still get enough oxygen in their bodies.
@就是槭颤N 蜻蜓可以和老一哟
That's why the dragonflies here are as big as eagles
千足x和and the millipedes the size of alligators.
那N槭颤N那r候有如此充足的氧饽
So why was there so much oxygen back then?
其它都由一全新的生物u造的
It was produced by a new kind of life.
宇宙大探索
第九集
是什N拥纳物大影l生了@N』的化
What kind of life could've changed the Earth's atmosphere so dramatically?
@些⑻斓闹参
Plants that could reach for the sky
大
trees.
在它榱双@得光的中 M化出了抵抗引力的方式
In their competition for sunlight, trees evolved a way to defy gravity.
涑霈F以前 最高的植物
Before trees, the tallest vegetation was
只不^高及腰H
only about waist-high.
然後奇El生了
And then something wonderful happened.
一植物分子在度和性方面都@得了M化
A plant molecule evolved that was both strong and flexible,
@N材料可以支魏艽蟮闹亓
a material that could support a lot of weight,
也可以在L中曲而不折
yet bend in the wind without breaking.
木|素造就了涞恼Q生
Lignin made trees possible.
F在生命可以向上l展
Now life could build upward.
K且打_了一片全新的I域
And this opened a whole new territory,
@些hx地面的群w形成一三S的世界
a three-dimensional matrix for communities far above the ground.
地球成了涞氖澜
Earth became the Planet of the Trees.
但是木|素有缺c
But lignin had a downside
不易食
it was hard to swallow.
天然拆wk成T 真菌和菌
When nature's demolition crew, the fungi and bacteria,
消化一切有木|素的物w
tried to eat anything with lignin in it,
Y果就是乐氐南化不良
they got a really bad case of indigestion.
白要在至少1|年後才M化出
And termites wouldn't evolve for at least another 100 million years.
拿那些死掉的湓觞Nk呢
What to do with all those dead trees?
真菌和菌花M了装偃f年
It took the fungi and bacteria millions of years
才M化出消化它的化W方法
to evolve the biochemical means to consume them.
c此同r 洳嗟厣L
Meanwhile, the trees just kept springing up,
死亡 倒下
dying, falling over
再由f年e累的泥土覆w
and getting buried by the mud that built up over eons.
最K |f的
Eventually, there were hundreds of billions of trees
被深埋地下
entombed in the Earth,
被埋葬在世界各地的森林
buried forests all over the Earth.
那硎颤N在的危害呢
What possible harm could come from that?
新斯科问〉倪@已率橇硪环N年v
This cliff in Nova Scotia is another kind of calendar.
它Vf著另一曾在@Y繁s世界的故事
It tells the story of that other world that once flourished right here.
@是一棵3|年古涞乃劳雒婢
And this is the death mask of that 300 million-year-old tree.
它由V物打造 V物替代了原本的木^
It was cast by minerals that replaced the original wood
替代了每一胞 它又被Q 化石
cell by cell-- in other words, a fossil.
很久以前 ⑺的有C分子U散到周的h境中
The tree surrendered its organic molecules to the environment long ago,
包括碳元素和水分 只留下它的形
its carbon and water. Only its shape remains.
@棵溥活著r 它吸入二氧化碳
When this tree was alive, it took in carbon dioxide
有水分 利用光
and water and used sunlight
把它D化成富含能量的有C物
to turn them into energy-rich organic matter.
然後把氧庾U物排出
The tree gave off oxygen as a waste product.
至今浜推渌植物依然是@幼龅
That's what trees and other plants still do.
植物死亡後 它腐
When plants die, they decay,
K且反D那^程
and this reverses the transaction.
它的有C物c氧饨Y合
Their organic matter combines with oxygen
然後分解
and decomposes,
⒍氧化碳排放到空庵
putting carbon dioxide back into the air.
@使得地球大拥幕W物|_到平衡
This balances the books for the chemistry of Earth's atmosphere.
如果湓诟前就被埋葬
But if the trees are buried before they can decay,
那l生杉事 它е碳元素
two things happen... they take the carbon
K⑻能Σ卦谘Y面
and stored solar energy with them
不ё哐
and leave the oxygen behind
任由它在大庵蟹e累
to build up in the atmosphere.
@就是3|年前的r
That's what happened around 300 million years ago.
r氧膺^剩
There was an oxygen surplus.
因此x子可以L得如此巨大
That's how the bugs got so big.
那些被掩埋的碳又怎幽
And what became of all that buried carbon?
它c世隔^ 深埋地下|f年
It lay there for eons before dealing life on Earth
然後l生了有史以碜罹缧缘谋l
its most devastating blow of all time.
在地球上有些地方 你可以跨越rg
There are places on this planet where you can walk through time
x岩石中N含的v史
and read the history written in the rocks.
新斯科问〉暮┚褪沁@拥囊地方
This beach in Nova Scotia is one of them.
每一佣际且豁
Every layer is a page.
每一佣荚Vf著一大洪水的故事
Each one tells the story of a flood,
一接一 持m装偃f年
one after another, over millions of years.
像A心蛋糕一拥暮樗沉e 逐u被掩埋
The layer cake of flood deposits was slowly buried
在囟群毫Φ淖饔孟 檠沂
and turned into rock by heat and pressure.
@些同拥牧α慨a生了山}
The same forces that built mountains
B同被埋葬的化石森林一起
then tilted and uplifted them,
在它的基A上 A斜再慢慢e高
along with the entombed fossil forest.
新的岩涌是堆e在老的岩又上
The newer layers were always deposited on top of the older ones.
就如所有的都按照正_的序排列
All the pages are in the correct order,
著装偃f年磉@Y曾的故事
bearing witness to what happened here over millions of years.
後面那Y 藏著更古老的^去
Back that way lies the more distant past.
我每向前走一步
And with every step I take,
相於向F在~M1千年
I move about 1,000 years closer to the present
同rhx那3|年前的世界
and away from the world of 300 million years ago.
那就是5千f年後
50 million years later lies that way.
@是二Bo末期的_始
This was the beginning of the end of the Permian world,
也就是一oc比的大缃^
an event of unequalled carnage.
二Bo是缃^o念堂Y
The Permian is the darkest corridor
最沉重的一l走廊 也是o念生命之渖
in this memorial to the broken branches on the Tree of Life--
其中的一根嘀
the Halls of Extinction.
2|5千f年
Death has never come so close
死神]像@影 想要y治整世界
to reigning supreme on this world in the quarter billion years since.
在F今西伯利l生的火山爆l
The eruptions, in what is now Siberia,
持m了资f年
lasted for hundreds of thousands of years.
熔The lava flooded and buried more than a million square miles.
@次的碾y使其他v史r期的火山爆l相形I
This event dwarfs any volcanic eruption in historical times.
缃^o念堂
幕鹕搅芽p中出大量的二氧化碳
Huge quantities of carbon dioxide came pouring out of the volcanic fissures
@厥怏w使得大囟炔嗯噬
This greenhouse gas warmed the climate.
使得早先在石炭o就被埋葬的森林再次回到我的故事中
And this is where the long-buried forests of the earlier Carboniferous Period reenter the story.
在5千f年的rgY
During the intervening 50 million years,
那些渥成了巨大的煤V
those trees had turned into immense deposits of coal,
就因檫@
and as it happened,
世界上最大α康拿旱V之一
one of the world's largest accumulations of coal
就被埋在西伯利
was buried right there in Siberia.
熔岩的囟群婵局煤
The heat from the lava baked the coal,
促使沼夂透涣怏wn出地表
driving methane and sulfur-rich gases out of the ground.
同rMd著有毒的放射性m埃微粒
They were laden with toxic and radioactive ash particles
@就是煤
coal smoke.
@N邪旱幕旌衔空庠斐闪乐氐奈廴
This witch's brew polluted the atmosphere
也母本上е铝说厍囟鹊氖Ш
and radically destabilized Earth's climate.
硫酸F霾隔^了光 使地球陷入黑暗
A sulfuric acid haze blocked incoming sunlight and darkened the planet
全球囟润E降至冰c以下
Global temperatures plummeted to subfreezing.
在火山l的g歇期
During lulls in the eruptions,
硫酸F霾落回地面
the acid haze fell back to the surface.
但是二氧化碳^m
But the carbon dioxide remained
在空庵欣鄯e е氯球暖
and built up in the atmosphere to cause global warming.
多年的篮c上千年的酷峤惶娉霈F
Years of frigid cold alternating with millennia of stifling heat
е铝又参锏盗p少
battered a dwindling population of plants and animals.
它]有C去m×业刈化
They had no chance to adapt to the drastic swings in climate.
S著全球暖的持m
As the global warmingcontinued,
表雍蜕拥乃逐u混合
the surface and the bottom waters slowly mixed,
使曾冰冷的海床水厣高
raising the temperature of the once-frigid depths of the sea floor.
令沉e物中富含沼獾谋也_始融化
Methane-rich ices that had been frozen in the sediments began to melt.
重@自由的沼飧∩纤面K且M入空庵
Newly liberated methane gas made its way to the surface and into the atmosphere.
而沼獗榷氧化碳能蚋有效地吸收崃
Methane traps heat far more efficiently than carbon dioxide
於是夂蜃得更炎
so the climate got even hotter.
沼庖财牧肆似搅又械某粞
And the methane also destroyed the ozone layer in the stratosphere
保o生物不受致命紫外害的天然防袼 已被侵g了
The natural sunscreen that protects life from deadly ultraviolet rays was eaten away.
全球海洋的循h系y停止了工作
The circulatory system of the world ocean shut down.
水Y的空夂谋M
These stagnant waters became oxygen-starved,
⑺懒舜蠛Ｖ缀跛有的~
killing almost all the fish in the sea.
但有一N生物在@酷的h境中得以繁s
But one kind of life flourished in this brutal environment...
那是能排泄出硫化涞囊环N菌
bacteria that produced deadly hydrogen sulfide gas as a waste product.
它也是核礼的最後一根稻草
That was the last straw.
有毒怏w⑺懒岁地上缀跗渌所有的植物和游
The poison gas killed almost all the remaining plants and animals on the land.
@就是大缃^
This was the Great Dying.
地球上生命最接近全部缃^的一次
The closest life on Earth has ever come to annihilation.
十分之九的物N不痛嬖
Nine in ten of all species perished.
地球花M了很久才使生命重燃生C
It took a long time for life to bounce back.
而@装偃f年 地球可以用
For a few million years, Earth could have been called
"死獬脸"硇稳
the Planet of the Dead.
我的祖先是少存物N之一
We are descended from one of the few species that managed to squeak by
你作槿祟 K且F在能存在
You are human and alive at this very moment
都w功於它DNA
because they managed to endure, conveying
倪@生物v史上最危U的r期
their DNA through one of the most treacherous periods
延m下
in the history of life.
@座山}完全由生物M成
This mountain was made entirely by life.
在地z大T大_之前
The life that flourished back in the glory days
@些生物都曾在二Bo有著x煌的^去
of the Permian, before all hell broke loose.
@Y是L_400英里的瓜_普山}的一部分
This is part of the 400 mile-long
穿德克_斯和新墨西哥州
Guadalupe Mountain chain that runs through Texas and New Mexico
世界上最大的化石r礁
It's the world's largest fossil reef.
@Y曾是一大片汝海
All this was once a great inland sea.
@r礁欣欣向s了好装倌
The reef flourished and grew for millions of years,
她曾是海d生物 G藻生物
and was home to multitudes of sponges, green algae,
有很多小得看不的生物以樯的家
and animals too small to see.
@些生物死亡後
When these creatures died,
它沉到海底 K被淤泥覆w
they sank to the bottom and were buried in the silt.
装偃f年後
Over millions of years,
它的骸成石油和天然
their remains were converted into oil and gas.
最K 盆地被淤泥填M r礁死亡
Eventually, the basin silted in and the reef died.
然後 @座海底鬼城被深埋在地下一英里
This marine ghost town was then buried a mile beneath the surface.
後 造作用力Ⅶ俭t般的r礁推上海平面
Later, tectonic forces lifted the skeletal reef high above sea level,
於是它又被L雨侵g了o的
where it was eroded and sculpted over eons by wind and rain.
想像一下@Y2.75|年前的幼
Just imagine what this place looked like 275 million years ago,
那r候的汝海有鬃小u在海中漂浮著 海水Y充M了生
when it was a vibrant, tropical inland sea, dotted with islands
生命之火在那熊熊燃著
and brimming with life.
而在大s2.2|年前
Until about 220 million years ago,
新英格m和北美洲靠得很近
New England and North Africa were next-door neighbors.
那r]有大西洋
There was no such thing as the Atlantic Ocean.
中g那些Those thin blue fingers at the center-- they were lakes.
它是超大分裂的最初@著苏I
They were the first outward signs that the supercontinent
同r也A示了地球上的生命⒂碛忠淮蔚木拮
was splitting apart and that life on Earth was due for another big shake-up.
1百f年後 @些湖成了一lLL的海
A million years later, the lakes became a long bay,
然後逐u成大西洋
which would grow into the Atlantic Ocean.
地表的@些意x重大的化
These profound changes at the surface
shho法c地球深l生的化相提K
were merely symptoms of a drama that was unfolding far beneath, in the depths of the Earth.
人出Fr @些可以揭示地球∽的
By the time we got here, the telltale traces
蛛zRE已被淹]在大洋深
of global upheaval were buried at the bottom of the deep blue sea.
我已完全不清楚地球酷o比的^去
We were completely cut off from the great story of Earth's violent past
就像失Y患者一悠惹械南胍知道
a species of amnesiacs trying to find out
他是l 以前究竟l生了什N
who we were and what happened before we awakened.
1570年伯拉罕・W特柳斯Lu了首
In 1570, Abraham Ortelius created the first
F代世界地D 都w功於
modern world atlas, reflecting on the discoveries
^去80年嶂蕴剿鞯狞S金r代Y的ゴ蟀lF
of the previous 80 years-- the Golden Age of Exploration.
]等墨E乾透
Before the ink was dry,
W特柳斯便已_始仔他的茏
Ortelius stepped back from his masterpiece
他首先lF了
and became the first of many to notice the striking
大西洋鹊拇箨相互吻合
puzzle-piece fit between the continent on either side of the Atlantic.
他S後道 美洲是因榈卣鸷秃樗
He later wrote that the Americas were torn away
才cW非大分x_
from Europe and Africa by earthquakes and floods.
但是W特柳斯的^察Y
But Ortelius's observation
在S後的装倌暄Y 都被J槟侵徊贿^是他的直X而已
remained nothing more than a hunch for the next couple of centuries...
直到20世o早期
until an early 20th century
德的一位天文W家兼庀W家
German astronomer and meteorologist
才用e累的C 使之成橐科W理
amassed the evidence to build the scientific case for it.
第一次世界大鹌陂g 阿弗雷德・魏格Alfred Wegener had been drafted during the First World War,
不久就
but was wounded soon after.
在鸬蒯t院恢推陂g
As he recovered in a field hospital,
他目W文I中搜さ厍蛲事的索
he scoured scientific literature for clues to the Earth's past.
多年前
Years before,
魏格Wegener had happened upon an intriguing paper in the stacks of his university library.
魏格It puzzled Wegener
F在已缃^的同N蕨化石
that fossils of the same species of a now-extinct fern
竟然在大西洋砂抖加邪lF它的蟮
were reported to be found on both sides of the Atlantic.
更令人@奇的是 同N的恐化石
Even more curious were the discoveries of fossils
也在蛇的大都有lF
of the same dinosaurs on both continents.
而在20世o早期
In the early 20th century,
地|W家@NF象做了解
geologists explained how life crossed the oceans
他想像K大g曾有一K地B接
by imagining that land bridges had once existed between them.
他相信@些B接的地在之前逐u瓦解
It was thought that these land bridges gradually disintegrated
然後消失在海底了
and vanished beneath the waves long ago.
但是有一C使得魏格But there was one piece of evidence that convinced Wegener
@主流的科W^c肯定e了
that the prevailing scientific view must be wrong...
C就是地球本身
the Earth itself.
一l山}怎N跨越海洋的分割
Why would a mountain range cross the oceanic divide
又在另一K大^md延
to continue on another continent?
槭颤N巴西和南非所lF的岩石
And why would you find the same unique pattern
有著相同的特造律
in the layers of rocks in both Brazil and South Africa?
有
And another thing...
槭颤NУ闹参
under what circumstances could tropical plants have flourished
居然出F在北冰洋的冰天雪地中
in the frozen wastes of the Arctic?
魏格Wegener concluded that there was only one logical solution to this puzzle...
地球上曾有一K超大
There had once been a single supercontinent on Earth.
他Q之 P古大
He named it Pangaea.
魏格So Wegener becomes the toast of the scientific world, right?
K]有
Not exactly.
大多档牡刭|W家嘲笑他的大漂移猜想
Most geologists ridiculed Wegener's hypothesis of continental drift.
他更A向於用他的天然地B接理
They preferred their imaginary natural land bridges
ξ焊窦to explain away Wegener's evidence.
他|疑大怎N可能破_海床杂驳难沂呢
How, they asked, could a continent plow through the solid rock of the ocean floor?
魏格Wegener had no convincing answer.
他成了@I域的笑柄
He became the laughingstock of the field;
Wgh中的
a pariah at scientific conferences.
管如此 魏格Despite this, Wegener continued to fight for his ideas,
榱耸占CM行大的科W研究考察
conducting daring research expeditions to gather evidence.
其中又一次 他得知同事
On one of these, he learned that colleagues were
被困在冰冠中 ]有食物
trapped on an ice cap without food.
在他增援後的返回途中
On his way back from the mission,
他迷失在了暴L雪中
he became lost in a blizzard.
就在他50q生日^後的一商
A day or two after his 50th birthday,
他失了
he disappeared,
他永h不知道 他的^c被C明是正_的 而他被
he would be vindicated and come to be viewed
v史上最ゴ蟮牡刭|W家之一
as one of the greatest geologists in history.
科W家也是人
Scientists are human.
也有盲c和偏
We have our blind spots and prejudices.
科W是一NC制 就是要叱@些盲c和偏
Science is a mechanism designed to ferret them out
}是 我K非一直忠\於@科W的核心r值
Problem is, we aren't always faithful to the core values of science
・_普就深知其中的精髓
Few people knew this better than Marie Tharp.
1952年 耐心地忍受著地|系同事的p
It's 1952, and Marie is patiently enduring the slights of her fellow members of the geology department.
她的地|WW位和WIK不被他放在眼Y
Her degrees in geology and mathematics count for little with them.
布斯・希森 一位酆扇A州淼难芯可
Bruce Heezen, a graduate student from Iowa,
Y束了漫L的科考探U
has just returned from a lengthy expedition
他用to map the ocean floor using sonar.
你能看看@些能用碜鍪颤N吧
Will you do something with these?
布斯 你瞧
Bruce, look.
一切都很明t
It's-- it's all come together.
@l大裂谷
There's this giant rift valley
穿整大西洋底部
that runs through the bottom of the Atlantic.
得了吧
Aw, geez, Marie, come on.
又是@些U
This is just more girl talk.
你]受蛩Ыo你的麻
You're not in enough trouble with everyone here already?
@直就是大漂移理
This sounds too much like continental drift.
你想S落到魏格You want to end up like Wegener?
但是不樗
But Marie would not be dissuaded.
多年後 和布斯⒁海洋震央D
Years later, when Marie and Bruce placed a map of oceanic
放上看片台 w在她的海底地D上r
earthquake epicenters on a light table over her seafloor map,
地震c遍颜大裂谷
the earthquakes fell right along the rift valley.
@就是魏格This was the smoking gun for Wegener's moving continents.
海底山脊的最高c
希森K於知道
Heezen now knew
原憩一直都是Φ
that Marie had been right all along.
他共同Lu了第一真正意x上的地球地D
Together, they created the first true map of the Earth,
包括了海底
including the ocean floor.
@使得我K於可以_始解x地球的自
We were at last ready to read the autobiography of the Earth.
我乘坐想像之舟
Let's take the Ship of the Imagination...
M入Υ蟛糠秩碚f的都是深不可及的地方
to a part of the world that has been off-limits to all but a few of us
地球的三分之二
Two-thirds of the Earth
都在1千英尺的水下
lies beneath more than 1,000 feet of water.
s300米左右
如此的V 大部分都未勘探
It's a vast and largely unexplored frontier.
所有人都知道阿卑斯山}和落基山}
Everybody knows the Alps and the Rockies,
但一些世界上最延^的山}都被[藏起砹
but some of the world's most amazing mountain ranges are hidden from view.
我到_水面下1千米@日光照射不到的世界
Below 1,000 meters, we enter a world where there is no sunlight.
一[藏在黑暗中的神奇世界
Hidden in the darkness, a world of wonders.
@是世界上最L的海底山}
This is the longest submarine mountain range in the world,
大西洋洋中脊
the Atlantic Mid-Ocean Ridge.
其M跨大西洋及北冰洋 每年都以5至10厘米的速度向|西方向成L
它在我的星球上形成一l宛如@球接p的
It wraps around our globe like the seam on a baseball.
在^去 我的星球cF在截然不同
The past is another planet,
但是大多等艘膊徊t解F在@星球
but most of us don't really know this one.
由於被水覆w 我看不@些山}
We don't see the mountains for the water.
@就是・_普最初想像的世界
This is the world that Marie Tharp was the first to imagine.
山脊的最高峰
The highest peaks of the ridge
超出海底4千米
rise over four kilometers above the ocean floor
有很多延d的山}和There are sprawling mountain ranges and canyons, too.
我F在M入RYWe've now entered the Marianas Trench,
海系靥北太平洋西方海床
海系撞快逗Ｆ矫嫦轮深度 h僦槟吕尸峰海平面上之高度
地球上最深的the deepest canyon on Earth,
超^1f米的深度
more than ten kilometers deep.
它形成造力⒑４餐D到
It formed when tectonic forces pushed the seabed
相的大板K下
under the adjoining continental plate.
上^月球的人
More people have walked on the Moon
比下磉@Y的多
than have ever been down here.
@Y的毫_到了每平方英8
The pressure here is a crushing eight tons per square inch.
@拥纳疃
Being this deep in the ocean
就像是50架波音747B在一起
is like having 50 jumbo jets stacked on top of you.
即使在@Y 也有生命的存在
Yet even here, life has taken hold.
管光o法穿^@N深的海水
The fact that sunlight can't penetrate the deep ocean
但K不意味著@Y]有光
doesn't mean there isn't light down here.
S多水下生物在暗中l光
Many underwater species glow in the dark,
我Q之樯物光
through a process called bioluminescence.
我作殛地上的哺乳游
Our long history as land mammals,
有著生活在光普照下的悠久v史
denizens of the sunlit world, hasn't prepared us
使我]有像海底深多N多拥纳物那拥倪M化
for the amazing variety of life that evolution has crafted in the deep oceans.
因檫@Y]有光
Since there's no sunlight down here,
也就]有光合作用
there's no photosynthesis.
意味著]有植物可供食用
That means there are no plants to feed on,
可即使在@右]有光的世界
and yet, even here, in a world of permanent midnight,
也有一l繁s的食物
there's a thriving food chain.
它由化W合成_始
It begins with a process called chemosynthesis
@些只有@微R下可的生物
These microscopic creatures have learned to eat
W了食用那孔Y出淼|西
what's pouring out of that vent...
一N被Q榱蚧涞挠卸净旌衔
a noxious compound called hydrogen sulfide.
那饷艿暮提供了化W能量
That thick black smoke provides the chemical energy
使得生命得以在此生存
that makes life possible here.
小甲游锍约菌
Tiny crustaceans eat the bacteria,
大一些的游锍孕〖游
and the larger animals eat the crustaceans.
地球未淼哪骋惶
One day, on some future Earth,
@些山}很有可能露出水面
these mountains could very well end up above the water.
造作用力持m改著地球的外貌
Tectonic forces continue to shape our planet.
未硪和F在截然不同
The future is also another planet.
以前 一像@拥幕鹕
It was a volcano like this one
在蛋偃f年前 造了夏威夷群u
that created the Hawaiian islands millions of years ago.
我住在一沸v大的外ど
We live on the crust of a seething cauldron.
地球的中心有一大F芯
At the center of our planet, there's an iron core.
它被包裹在一液w的F
It's nested inside of a larger, liquid iron shell.
再外拥牟糠址Q之榈蒯
Wrapped over this is the part called the mantle.
它是岩石成 s很岷莛
It's rocky but hot and viscous.
就像是t子上的一
Like a pot of soup cooking on a stove,
不嗟胤v
the mantle is churning.
是什N使它翻v呢
What keeps it moving?
|西 一是地球形成rz留的高
Two things... the heat left over from Earth's formation,
另一就是地核中放射性物|的衰
and the decay of radioactive elements in the core.
而@外 地
And this outer layer-- the crust,
你 我 大家所生活的地方
where you and me and everyone we know lives--
厚度s只相於O果皮
is only as thick as the skin on an apple.
地幔拖庸腆w的覆w右黄鹨
The mantle drags the solid overlying crust along with it.
冷峻杂驳牡K不S其所
The crust resists because it's cool and rigid.
久而久之 到_了R界c
From time to time, it reaches the breaking point.
到了那r 大地_始u晃
When that happens, the Earth quakes.
K不是有人不要受到土P
It's not because somebody misbehaved and is being punished.
它只是自然法t控制下的SC力
It's due to random forces that are governed by the laws of nature.
因槲生存的rg太短
Our sense of the stability of the Earth is an illusion
造成了我於地球定感的幻X\
due to the shortness of our lives.
如果我可以用地球本身的rg刻度^察
If we could watch our planet on its own timescale,
重大的化要用上百f年的rg才可以@F出
in which big changes take millions of years to play out,
那r我才可以看出它是怎拥囊B有Cw
we would see it as the dynamic organism it really is.
@是三Bo晚期r的世界
This is the world of the late Triassic period
距xF今s2|年
about 200 million years ago.
那小砘
That little guy?
是我的h古祖先之一
It's one of our distant ancestors.
它所在地方就是F在的新晌髦莸募~瓦克
He lived in Newark, New Jersey.
不你在地球上的什N地方
Wherever you walk on Earth...
你的_下都曾有一失落的世界
lost worlds lie buried beneath your feet.
5千f到1|年前
50 or 100 million years ago,
大部分貌似平常的地方
even the most seemingly ordinary places
都v了史般的化
have been the scene of epic change.
@些r壁就是P古大分裂的o念碑
These Palisades are a monument to the breakup of the supercontinent Pangaea.
Bm的火山l
The sequence of volcanic eruptions
使@些已е铝肆硪龃缃^
that made these cliffs also led to the next mass extinction--
@龃缃^宣告了三Bo的KY
the one that ended the Triassic world.
但是造成一物N缃^的大碾y
But a catastrophic extinction event for one species
s是另一物N的FC遇
is a golden opportunity for another.
三Bo的物N缃^o了
The Triassic extinctions offered one group
另一物N登上世界舞台中心的C
that had been around for a while the chance to take center stage.
恐愉快茁训厣活了大s1.7|年
The dinosaurs had a good, long run for 170 million years.
那r 印度是一u
Back then, India was an island.
每年向北方慢慢爬行子
It crept northward at the pace of a few inches per year
m然慢的 但也o法阻跛向洲靠n
on its slow but inexorable rendezvous with Asia.
然後 再一次
Then, once again,
地表下的熔岩
the molten rock beneath Earth's surface
射而出K且淹]了印度西部的大部分
burst forth and flooded a huge area of western India.
致命的一奶於降
The knockout punch literally came out of the blue.
一些装侔踔氐游
Few animals larger than a hundred pounds
陌准o晚期的大碾y中存下
survived the catastrophes of the late Cretaceous.
m埃黹L_翟碌暮冷黑夜
The dust cloud brought night and cold to the surface for months.
恐因|寒交迫而死
The dinosaurs froze and starved to death.
但有一些在地下躲避的小游
But there were small creatures who took shelter in the Earth.
等它再次出Fr
And when they emerged...
它lF以前的C食它 威they found that the monsters who had hunted and terrorized them were gone.
地球成了哺乳游锏奶煜
The Earth was becoming the Planet of the Mammals.
地球^m不嘧化著
And the Earth continued its ceaseless changing.
@Y曾是寸草不生的荒漠
This was once a desert where nothing could grow.
只有1百f平方英里的沙和}
It was a million square miles of sand and salt,
比F在地球上任何h境都要毫
far more hostile than any environment on Earth today.
白天囟雀叩目梢钥军I包
Daytime temperatures were hot enough to bake bread.
因樗在海面之下1英里
And it was more than a mile below sea level,
因此大罕痊F在高出50%
so the atmospheric pressure was about 50% higher than what we're used to.
很y想出有什Nh境比@更令人^望
It would be hard to think of a more unpromising environment on this planet.
在5百50f年前 在成海之前
Yet this was the basin of the Mediterranean five and a half million years ago,
@Y曾是地中海盆地
before it became a sea.
地球平o的rg是短旱
The Earth never stops moving for long.
大盆地西端的天然大水
The natural dam at the western end of the deep basin
倒塌了 可能是因榈卣
gave way, probably due to earthquakes.
洪砹
And the deluge began.
疵偷暮樗模甚至超^了尼加拉瓜大瀑布4f倍
The torrential waters rushed in at a rate 40,000 times greater than Niagara Falls,
在不到一年的rgY就⑦@|的荒漠成了地中海
turning a vast desert into the Mediterranean Sea... in less than a year
那r候人]有出F
There were as yet no humans
o法目睹著邀的大洪水
to witness this enormous flood,
也o法感@它造的美景
nor to admire the beauty it created.
c此同r 地球的另一端
Meanwhile, half a world away,
分_南北美洲的海a broad channel separated North and South America...
使洋流可以拇笪餮罅魅胩平洋
allowing ocean currents to flow from the Atlantic into the Pacific Ocean.
最K因造作用力逐uK大集合在一起
Tectonic forces gradually brought these two continents together
]合了海closing the channel and creating the Isthmus of Panama.
@重塑了全球洋流模式
This reorganized the worldwide pattern of ocean currents,
亩改了全球的夂
which, in turn, affected the global climate.
茂盛G色森林覆w的非洲
In Africa, the lush green forest canopy
成了一片荒
gave way to a sparser landscape.
一些ｉT生活在渖系奈锓N缃^了
Some species that were highly specialized for life in the trees became extinct
但一些多面手s可以
But the generalists, the ones that could find a way
找到一l生存之道
to make a living no matter what life threw at them,
那就是 忍耐 然後M化
endured and evolved.
我的h古祖先曾榱硕惚艿孛娴穆邮痴叨藏身於地底深
Our ancestors had once burrowed deep in the ground to avoid predators who stalked the surface.
恐缤鲠
But when the dinosaurs perished,
它重@天日
they emerged into the daylight,
o的赆
and over the eons, made new lives
又爬回渖
in the branches of the trees.
它l育出m合抓握的拇指和_趾
They developed opposable thumbs and toes
可以在渲gu 穿^的涔
for swinging from branch to branch, across the broad canopy of treetops,
亩M足它所有的需求
where all their needs were fulfilled.
它也可以短旱闹绷⑿凶
They could also walk upright, but only for short distances.
周溥@N多 它也不需要走很h
With so many trees around, they didn't have to go very far.
直到後 叵陆 渥得稀疏
But then it got colder, and the trees thinned out,
|的草原涌F出 我的祖先
broad grasslands sprang up, and our ancestors
被迫穿^草原ふ沂澄
were forced to traverse them in search of food.
在Т蟛菰上 @就需要一套完全不同的技巧了
You needed a totally different skill set to make it on the savanna.
以前 可以悠f地坐在渲ι
In the old days, you could sit perched on your tree branch
hh地就能看到大型科游
and watch the big cats from a safe distance.
F在 莶痛嬖
Now you were playing on the same dangerous field.
存者都是一些
The survivors were those who evolved the ability
可以用後肢L距x行走 K且能在必要r奔跑的
to walk great distances on their hind legs and to run when necessary.
@改了它^察世界的方式
This changed the way they looked at the world.
行走r不再必要有手和胳膊的椭
Hands and arms were no longer tied up with walking.
它可以自由的收集食物 拾取渲和骨^
They were free to gather food and pick up sticks and bones.
用硌u造武器和工具
These could be used as weapons and tools.
想想看
Think of it...
一小K土地上的地形化
A change in the topography of a small piece of land
再加上地球另一端的洋流化
half a world away reroutes ocean currents.
使得非洲得更冷更乾燥
Africa grows colder and drier.
大多档o法m新的夂
Most of the trees can't withstand the new climate.
生活在其中的`L
The primates who lived in them
必要ふ倚碌募@ 不知不X中
have to seek other homes, and before you know it,
它使用工具_始改造@星球
they're using tools to remake the planet.
地球改了人的命\
The Earth has shaped the course of human destiny,
有bh世界的看不的引力
but so has the invisible pull of distant worlds.
行星影著我的生活
The planets have influenced our lives
不是你想的那意思
but not in the way you think.
金星的引力
The gravitational pull of Venus--
不s很近
small but close--
木星的引力mhs很
and that of Jupiter-- distant but massive--
⒌厍虻妮S心拉向一 一@一那
tilted the Earth's axis this way and that...
K且微地扭曲了它的道
and ever so slightly tweaked the shape of its orbit.
@也L期性地改了光照射在北部冰冠的盗
This periodically altered the amount of sunlight falling on the edge of the northern ice cap.
有r使那Y的夏天更冷
Sometimes it made the summers there colder,
K使冰川向南移
and the glaciers advanced southward
年鸵荒
from one year to the next,
碾憾^
grinding and scraping,
摧а赝镜囊磺
and crushing everything in their path.
那就是我f的冰河r期
That's what we call an ice age.
而另一rg 地球S心和道的化
At other times, changes in Earth's axis and orbit
使北O的夏天更
made the Arctic summers warmer.
K使冰川融化 向後退s
And the melting glaciers began to retreat.
想像一下我的祖先要有多大的本事
Imagine how resourceful our ancestors had to be
才能在@N夂虻木拮中存下
in order to survive these radical changes in climate.
每冰河r期
With each glacial period,
冰原都在侵g著海洋
the ice sheets grow at the expense of the oceans;
海平面下降超^400英尺
the world sea level falls by more than 400 feet,
s122米
沿著大的 使其露出大量的地
uncovering wide areas of land along the edges of the continents.
在1.5f到2.5f年前
15,000 to 25,000 years ago,
有^一次冰原後s
there was a period when the ice receded,
r露出了一段B接的地
exposing a temporary land bridge.
通向地球另一半的大T_
The gateway to the other half of the planet swings open.
成群Y的流浪者通^B接的地
Bands of wanderers crossed the land bridge
淼奖泵乐 有些去了南美洲
to North America and parts south.
大s1f年前
About 10,000 years ago
夂蚝秃Ｆ矫娴姆锤沧化停止了
the manic swings of the climate and sea levels came to a stop.
一鲂碌母睾偷夂r期到砹
A new and gentler climate age began.
就是我F在生活的r期
It's the one we live in now.
巨大的冰原融化r
When the great ice sheets melted,
海水升到F在的高度
the sea rose to its present height
河水yЦ叩囟淼哪嗌
and the rivers carried silt from the highlands
在流入大海r形成了河口_e平原
to build great delta plains where they met the sea.
在那些富的平原上 我W了全新的生活方式
On those fertile plains, we learned a new way of life...
如何N植食物以解Q|I
how to grow things, to feed ourselves and more.
Υ蟛糠秩碚f @意味著一百f年的[Y束了
For most of us, this meant an end to a million years of wandering.
行星g的相互吸引
The way the planets tug at each other,
地球表面的移
the way the skin of the Earth moves,
@些\於夂虻挠绊
the way those motions affect climate
於生命和智力M化的影
and the evolution of life and intelligence
它集合在一起 使我可以
they all combined to give us the means
河口_e平原的淤泥
to turn the mud of those river deltas
D樽畛醯奈拿
into the first civilizations.
g冰期是一o二的
There's nothing like an interglacial period,
冰河r期中的一段嘏舒m的g歇
one of those balmy intermissions in an ice age.
好消息是@r期 持m
And the great news is that this one is due to last
5f年
for another 50,000 years.
我可以口饬
What a break for our kind.
有一}
Just one problem.
我貌似不停的消耗@些
We can't seem to stop burning up all those
氖炭o就深埋地下的淠
buried trees from way back in the Carboniferous Age,
它已是煤炭了
in the form of coal;
有古代浮游生物的z骸
and the remains of ancient plankton,
F在是石油和天然饬
in the form of oil and gas.
如果可以停止 夂蛏碚f 我就x危U了
If we could, we'd be home free, climate-wise.
然而 我向空庵信欧哦氧化碳的速度
Instead, we're dumping carbon dioxide into the atmosphere
是自^去那е麓缃^的碾y以
at a rate the Earth hasn't seen since the great climate catastrophes of the past,
前所未有的快
the ones that led to mass extinctions.
我好像o法戒除我@些燃料的迷
We just can't seem to break our addiction to the kinds of fuel
]有意R到@把我Щ乜铸r代的夂
that'll bring back a climate last seen by the dinosaurs;
在那N夂蛳 我的沿海城市被淹]
a climate that will drown our coastal cities and wreak havoc
同r也乐仄奈的木澈陀绊我的食物
on the environment and our ability to feed ourselves.
一直以 邀的太
All the while, the glorious sun
⑾Q 免M的能量
pours immaculate, free energy down upon us;
hh超^我的需要
more than we will ever need.
我槭颤N不能W
Why can't we summon the ingenuity and courage
古人的智慧和勇饽
of the generations that came before us?
既然恐]有A到小行星的砼R
The dinosaurs never saw that asteroid coming.
槭颤N我不引前之b呢
What's our excuse?
有一l走廊
There's a corridor
就在缃^o念堂
in the Halls of Extinction that is, right now,
依然空空
empty and unmarked.
地球的自饕琅f^m
The autobiography of the Earth is still being written.
有可能我的故事就在此KY
There's a chance that the end of our story lies in there.
恭喜你
Congratulations.
你活著
You're alive.
一l不g嗟木
There's an unbroken thread that stretches across
d延跨越30|年
more than three billion years
⑽c@世界上
that connects us to the first life
第一生命M起
that ever touched this world.
想想我o档倪h古祖先有多N的
Think of how tough, resourceful and lucky
明 和幸\
all of our countless ancestors must have been
生存至今
to survive long enough
⑸命的信息
to pass on the message of life to the next
一代又一代
and the next...
^m接著一代又一代
and the next generation,
一直代代相
hundreds of millions of times...
鞯轿@一代
before it came to us.
需要跨^多少河流
There were so many rivers to cross,
期g有o档恼系K
so many hazards along the way.
C食者 荒 疾病
Predators, starvation, disease,
π莸恼`判 漫L的寒冬
miscalculation, long winters,
旱 洪 暴力
drought, flood and violence.
有偶牡叵l的火山
Not to mention the occasional upheavals that erupted from within our planet
和天上落下的末日天w
and the apocalyptic bolts that come from the blue.
o奈起源何
No matter where we hail from
我的祖先是l
or who our parents were, we are descended
我都是不可思h的大碾y的存者
from the hearty survivors of unimaginable catastrophes.
每人都是在最漫L最危U的接力中的①者
Each of us is a runner in the longest and most dangerous relay race there ever was,
此r此刻 接力棒就在我的手中
and at this moment, we hold the baton in our hands.
^去是截然不同的世界
The past is another planet.
未⑹侨绱
And so is the future.
大s2.5|年後
Some 250 million years from now,
S多地|W家J榈厍蛏系年地
many geologists think that the lands of the Earth
再次聚合在一起
will be united once again.
@些美景⒉痛嬖
All this beauty will have vanished
我此r的地球
and the Earth of our moment in time
就成了那r的失落世界
will take its place among the lost worlds.
板K造的ゴ炔恿
The great internal engine of plate tectonics
ι命漠不P心
is indifferent to life,
就如同地球道和S心的微化
as are the small changes in the Earth's orbit and tilt
有偶碜孕√祗w的撞
and the occasional collisions with little worlds on rogue orbits.
@些活於我星球表面资|年Y
These processes have no notion of what has been going on
l生的事情完全]有概念
over billions of years on our planet's surface.
它不在乎
They do not care.
每人都只是@w小行星
Each of us is a tiny being
外ど系某丝
riding on the outermost skin of one of the smaller planets
@著自己的a星走上资圈
for a few dozen trips around the local star.
地球上最古老的生物
The things that live the longest on Earth
也只不^猿至说厍蚰挲g的百f分之一
endure for only about a millionth of the age of our planet.
然 任何一有Cw
So, of course, the individual organisms
是不可能看到
see nothing of the overall pattern.
大化的全貌
Of changing continents...
夂蜃化的全貌
climate...
M化的全貌
evolution.
我明白 我的小小起源
That we understand even a little of our origins
都是人洞察和勇獾ゴ倮之一
is one of the great triumphs of human insight and courage.
我是l 我怎N淼竭@Y
Who we are and why we are here can only be glimpsed
答案只能通^拼零星的碎片@得
by piecing together something of the full picture,
完整的答案必然包含o档rg
which must encompass eons of time...
装偃fN物N
millions of species...
有一大批的不同天w
and a multitude of worlds.
以@角度看也不用感到奇怪
In this perspective, it's not surprising
那是因槲本身就是一i
that we're a mystery to ourselves and that,
管我很自豪
despite our manifest pretension,
但我不是@小星球上的主人
we are far from being masters of our own little house.
@l走廊入口]有代表它的o元的名Q
This new corridor has no name above the entrance to designate its epoch, and we don't yet know
也不知道哪缤龅奈锓N被煸上作榧o念
which failed species will be memorialized within its walls.
F在l生的一切 有o档目赡 可大可小
What happens here, in countless ways, both large and small,
而@一切都取Q於我
is being written by us.
F在的我
Right now.